<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Vishwanath Varma</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Collective exploration and learning</title>
      <link>/project/collective-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/collective-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Fish can individually learn spatial features in their habitat but often use cues from other individuals to navigate. Here, we are examining how pairs of fish learn a spatial maze and whether the time taken to reach the reward is dependent on the extent of exploration exhibited by individual fish or the degree of coordination within the pair. We are also trying to model the sequential exploration of the maze and the use of social cues in this navigation process.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Personality and social behaviour in Mahseer</title>
      <link>/project/social-interactions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/social-interactions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Deccan Mahseer is an endangered freshwater fish indigenous to the rivers of Southern and Central India. The declining populations of these fish are being supplemented by hatchery reared fish that are being reintroduced into these waters. Since hatchery reared fish typically have behavioural deficits which may lead to lower fitness and thus, inefficient restocking outcomes, we are looking at social learning as a possible means of mitigating such adverse effects. Since social learning depends on association with other individuals which in turn is related to behavioural traits such as exploration and sociability, we have constructed a detailed behavioural profile of these fish.&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/project/social-interactions/mahseer.jpg&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/project/social-interactions/mahseer.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fish can also change their behaviours based on their social environment. Modulation of social environment could be used to tweak the behavioural profiles of fish to suit the environment into which they will be released. We are now looking at how risk-taking behaviour changes based on the personality of a shoaling partner. We also attempt to analyze the nature of social interactions and the behavioural changes induced by these interactions using an agent-based model of a fish pair.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accuracy of circadian rhythms</title>
      <link>/project/rhythm-accuracy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/rhythm-accuracy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We investigated the factors that influence the ability of the internal clock in flies to synchronize with the external environment with a consistent phase of entrainment. My main project involved artificial selection on fly populations for daily emergence as adults within a window of one hour during the daytime. Another project examined the interaction between internal clock period and length of the external cycle in determining accuracy of mutant flies with different periodicities.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Daily rhythms under semi-natural conditions</title>
      <link>/project/natural-rhythms/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/natural-rhythms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We performed some of the first experiments on Drosophila activity and adult emergence rhythms in natural-like environments and found substantial differences in patterns of such behaviour compared to laboratory conditions. We examined the responsiveness of adult emergence to environmental variables such as temperature and humidity and showed that flies tend to emerge close to the time when minimum temperature and maximum humidity is seen. Moreover, we manipulated light patterns in natural environments using filters and shades to show that different peaks of activity are differently modulated by light and temperature and may correspond to functionally different behaviours such as foraging or mating. We also showed that light receptor and internal clock mutants show largely similar behaviour to controls in semi-natural conditions as opposed to the large differences seen in laboratory.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Miscellaneous side-projects</title>
      <link>/project/miscellaneous/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/miscellaneous/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Jetlag is the process of re-adjusting the internal clock to a change in the timing of the external cycle and is mediated by delaying or advancing the internal clock (also called phase-shifting in circadian parlance). We showed that the perturbation of a simple limit cycle model of an internal clock using a light pulse can be used to predict how rates of jetlag (or magnitude of phase-shifts) might differ at different temperatures in fruit flies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a separate study, we report the interesting finding that virgin female flies also exhibit a rhythm in egg-laying and , in fact, show more robust rhythmicity compared to mated females, which can be partially explained by the presence of a male.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another series of studies, that I was a part of, demonstrated that circadian clocks persist for over 300 generations in fly populations maintained under constant light and constant dark environments (where presumably there is no advantage of synchronizing internal clocks to the external environment). We suggest that either there are intrinsic benefits of coordinating the timing of physiological events or clock genes are pleiotropic and involved in multiple functions in addition to circadian time-keeping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also co-designed a simple experiment to show that male flies have residual sexual drive (evening peak of locomotor activity) after mating with a single female which dissipates upon mating with multiple females. In contrast, female flies only show a generic effect of mating (reduction of evening activity peak or sex drive) irrespective of the number of partners.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
